At the point of recording this,
I have 421,877
subscribers on my main channel,
and I've stopped using this account
altogether because I
was making the biggest mistake
that most YouTubers make.
I didn't even see that I
was making the mistake.
And in this video,
I'm going to hopefully stop you from
making the mistake that I
made,
and you'll understand why I'm very excited
about my new little
channel with 5,736 subscribers.
The biggest
mistake that I was making with the big
channel is I was just trying to be a big
YouTube channel.
I got really excited about the silver play
button.
I was thinking, "Oh, wow.
I could get the gold play button."
And I wasn't really
making the right type of content
or growing the right type of audience.
For any of you out there
that want to make a YouTube channel,
you might think that
the way you conquer YouTube
is you get millions of subscribers,
and then
the AdSense revenue starts coming in.
You get thousands of pounds from YouTube,
and then you can just retire, and you put
up a video, and you get 20 grand.
For some people, that works.
If you're Logan Paul, if you're MrBeast,
or one of the most recent sensations,
Matt Armstrong, who
is a UK creator who buys crash-damaged
cars
and fixes them up,
who gets a million views within 12 hours
of posting,
sure. That can be a way of making money.
But that's a lot of stress on you.
Now, let's imagine that your business
is you're an online coach, or that you
are a
videographer,
like Declan here behind the camera.
Let's say you teach languages,
you teach people to swim,
or what would be another
person? You're a jujitsu black belt.
When making content, what do you think,
as far as longevity, profit
margins, whatever,
or let's say we're looking at metrics of
success, what do you
think would be better?
Getting a million views on each video
and every video having
to get that,
or having some kind of product in the
background?
Let's rewind,
and let me introduce you to a guy called
Ed, who runs a channel
called Film Booth and Creative Booth.
I spent 10,000 pounds with Ed to learn
about YouTube, and the
first thing that we spoke about on a
one-to-one call, he said, "So, what's your
business?" I said, "What do you mean,
what's my business?
I'm here for YouTube, brother.
I'm here to get them subscribers
and to get that
million." He goes,
"What's your business?" I was like,
"I have a PT business." He
goes, "Okay,
so how do you use the content to promote
your business?" I was like,
"What? Mate, I'm here to get famous.
I'm here to get stopped by 19-year-old
boys who go, 'Oh, you're that guy from
YouTube.'" He goes, "No.
The reason we have YouTube
is to promote our business, not
to become famous." I was like, "Oh,
okay." Because I have hundreds and
thousands of people
that subscribe to my main channel that
are what can only be
described as a subprime audience.
Instead of trying to bolster
and benefit my businesses on YouTube,
I was
just trying to be popular,
and I grew the account very fast.
But then,
when I go to release a product like
NuTonic,
you get torn apart by people in the
comments.
And then I realized, "Oh,
I've got a big audience of L-ends,"
rather than having a tight niche audience
of people that really care about the
knowledge that I can give.
On this channel,
the only 5,000 subscribers at the time
of filming, when I say,
"There's a link to my email list in the
description," we
get a lot of people joining the email
list.
When I say,
"There's a link in the description where I
can give you 30 ways in 30
days to benefit your business," people
sign up.
When I put a link to my mentorship,
some people join.
I've only just realized
that having 5,000 people that are really,
really right for
your business is better than 500,000
people that aren't.
Crazier yet,
I'm more excited about my small channel
having a video that hits 10,000 views than
I am about my big channel hitting a
million.
Because I'm going to show you now.
Sure,
my video that I did on WHOOP made 12,000
pounds, which is incredible.
I just got a bunch of people that
were interested
in finding out if a wearable
was a good idea to purchase.
That didn't really do anything for my
brand or businesses.
If anything,
it just helped WHOOP's brand and business.
And I only spoke about WHOOP because I
knew that people on the internet were
interested. Whereas this video today,
if 12 people,
just 12 people out of the few thousand
people that watch it, join my
mentorship,
I will make more money than the 600,000
views on that video.
Now, what do you think,
as a creator sat at home watching this,
is easier?
To get a few thousand views
and 12 customers, or to get
550,000 views on a semi-viral reel about a
product called WHOOP?
And the worst thing is,
at the end of the day,
would you rather have millions of
views and money from Google,
or would you have a business?
And a business that can benefit people,
because the black belt, you can teach
people submissions, escapes, whatever.
The videographer,
you can teach people how to use DaVinci
Resolve,
Premiere Pro, how to make edits.
You can teach people to be self-sufficient
so
that they can approach businesses with a
camera and say, "Hey, I'm going to come
in, do a free content day for you,"
which is what Declan did.
It's how I ended up finding out about him.
Creating content for a local business
and brand,
and then getting hired referrals
by the mouth. Actually,
Declan behind the camera went to my barber
and said, "Let
me do some free social media creatives for
you." Then when I was moaning to my
barber that I needed a videographer,
he goes,
"I've got the man for you." What were
the other examples? Coaches,
personal trainers.
If you were to make a video
that only got 5,000 views teaching
people how to write their own programs,
it's guaranteed that at least five of
those
people are going to go, "Oh my god.
This person really understands
programming.
I'm going to hire them to write mine." So
straight away, before we get concerned
about having a small YouTube channel
and not getting enough views, we need to
completely rewrite the book.
If you make content just to be famous,
you're going to
explode a subprime audience of people
that aren't going to buy your book, go to
your events, hire your services,
or whatever.
And it's actually a lot of the niche
channels that probably make more money,
because their focus
is on creating a red-hot audience of
people that will buy their
products and services rather than trying
to appeal to everyone.
First thing, that's covered off.
How to make money on YouTube.
Make it a vessel
that works for your business.
Case in point, a few weeks ago,
I did a webinar on YouTube,
which you can access.
It's on this channel.
And I sat with someone who knows a lot
about YouTube, and he
kind of goes, "This title and thumbnail
is a little bit boring." I was like, "Do
you know what?
It is a bit boring." I called it a sales
and marketing masterclass,
or something like that. And in that, I
was teaching people how to operate a
business top to bottom.
So this guy called Marcus,
who's a YouTube expert, says to
me, "How much has your business made?"
And I went to Stripe, all time, $13.6
million. So he goes,
"Why not make your title, 'This
is how I made $13.6
million,' and in brackets,
'So you can steal it.'" I just made
that livestream
webinar more interesting. The views,
let me show you. Don't tell you, show you,
Declan.
Within a few days, I get a message,
"James, you've done $3,000 US
this week from the old video on your
YouTube that was posted a month ago."
YouTube,
for me,
is where I can put content that's
evergreen.
I have a million followers on Instagram,
I have a million followers on TikTok, I
have a million followers on Facebook.
But when you post there,
you get the engagement, and then it dies.
On YouTube,
I'm getting views trickle on videos
that are five, six months old.
Now,
that's great as far as revenue from the
whoop video, cool.
Might make 500 pounds this month, cool.
But do you know what excites me?
That people are sat watching a webinar
that I did six weeks ago.
They're listening to me talk about it for
an hour, then they're joining my paid
program.
Why would I get Google to pay me cents on
the views
when those same views,
when funneled to the right audience,
albeit smaller, could
get me thousands of dollars? And this
is a massive mindset change for me,
which I
couldn't believe.
Now I'm sat there thinking,
"Why am I going to post to this
sub-prime audience of 400,000
when I could help the prime audience of
5,000?" It's like,
would you rather go to a festival to try
and pick
up chicks, or why not go to a date night,
speed dating, where there's 20
women in a room, all keen, all up for it,
all fucking
ready to go? 60 seconds, speed date,
and everyone, they get 18 numbers on a
night out. Because you go to a festival,
you're wasting time chatting to people.
They're married, they're not interested.
They're there to listen to the music.
Why put yourself in an audience of
thousands when only a few want to shag,
when you
could go to an audience where everyone
wants to shag?
Do you want a big channel,
or do you want a big income?
Because there are a lot of creators
that are going broke.
We've seen this year a few creators burn
out and quit YouTube.
The reason was that they put so much
pressure and stress onto every video going
viral, that one of them, I think it
was Leon Hendrix, he spent two,
three weeks,
maybe even a month, making a video.
It got, like, 36,000 views, and it
was a really good video.
It just wasn't taken off by the algorithm.
And that crushes him,
because then his net position from
that video, he's down
thousands.
So you must position yourself to use
YouTube not like I did as a
vanity metric. Instead, as a vessel,
because you can hire a marketing
department. There
are empty desks in this room because I
hired people to
help me market my business.
They all quit because I'm a terrible
manager of employees,
and I have probably a bit of a complex
that I don't
think anyone's as good at marketing as me.
So when I leave them to do things like
email marketing, I look and I'm like,
"This
is awful." And when the last member of
staff, when she told me she was leaving,
she kind of was like, "James,
can we have a word for a second?"
And do you know
what I thought, Declan? I thought she
was going to tell me she was pregnant.
Not with me,
but pregnant in general.
Do you know what that means? Maternity.
Nine months paid leave.
When she told me she was quitting, I
was like, "Fucking
come on.
Come on!" So instead of having
that marketing department, I'm now
paying money to Declan to help me make
videos.
And do you know what my marketing
department is? Social media.
I take this video,
we will edit it together,
we'll chop it up, we'll put it into
the interweb,
and trickles of leads will appear over
months, and they will qualify
themselves. Any of you
that watched my videos before will know
that I put together
a very successful 30-day email
autoresponder, which
is in the description.
And every single day, everyone
that signs up to that list gets such an
impressive nugget of information
that the average person buys on day 19 to
day 24. So if you
were to create a YouTube series of videos
that
people were to watch and to binge through,
then at some point they're going to
click the link in the description.
Then via email you can pepper them until
they buy or they don't buy.
Either way,
it should be fine as long as your videos
are getting enough.
I know that we've spent a lot of time
there just talking about what YouTube is.
But if you don't understand that
and you start making banger videos,
for what?
A few grand here and there?
12K from a video is great,
but let's be real.
Average house price in Sydney.
Do you know how much that is, Declan?
1.4 million Australian dollars, which
is give or take 6,
700,000 US, give or take maybe 800,000
pounds in the UK. 12K is barely a deposit.
It's barely a stamp duty.
If you really want to do well on YouTube,
you want to be
making significantly more than that.
12K,
that'll only get you a private jet to
Ibiza one way.
As we'll find out next week. So
when you know what YouTube is,
we can move on to
the next step. How to use it.
Everything on social media is about value.
If you do not give value,
people do not care.
Personal trainers take pictures of their
lunch. No one cares.
People try and do testimonial videos about
what they worked with their...
No one cares. If you can reframe
that testimonial to say, "Hey, in this
video,
I'm going to give you five ways
that you can get more views on YouTube
without having to do any more work,"
and you were to reference people you've
worked
with as part of giving those lessons,
the testimonial works.
But if I just sit here and go,
"I worked with a coach called Eric,
and he makes a
million dollars a year because of the..."
You don't care.
You don't know Eric.
You don't give a fuck about Eric.
Every video has to have knowledge
and value in it, or people
are going to leave.
Similar to this one. So who
is your audience?
What problems do they face?
I am assuming right now most of you
are going to be
self-employed, sole traders, creators, or
probably 30% of you
are going to be dabbling one foot in
and one foot out of
another business. And you try
and get yourself into a position where you
force your
hand,
where you make so much money from your
online venture that you have to
quit your face-to-face business.
However,
I'm working with someone at the moment
who's a nurse, and they're
currently earning three times as much
being a nurse, must be from America, than
they are from their online coaching.
But I've said to that person,
"It's going to be very difficult to match
your salary
of where you are now doing coaching
part-time." So for any of you,
if your job is
paying you two grand a month,
when you get to 1,000 pounds a month,
or dollars
or whatever it is, with your coaching,
quit and go all in.
Because you can take the energy from the
current job you're doing, and
that's the only way you're going to be
able to match it.
So you can wait until you're earning the
same money, but it's going to be very,
very difficult. I would say
when you get to probably half of the
amount you're
getting from your full-time job, quit.
Because that 40 hours a week,
if you're in your 25, 26,
27 or your early 30s,
the amount of energy you have
is really finite, and it
is really limited. And
if you don't do this now
and you put it off two more years,
you are wasting energy.
So you need to make sure that you
are making the right
decision now. And if you are a nurse
or a fireman or whatever it is,
if your online venture dies within a year,
you can go back to your old job.
They'll take you back.
The majority of you out there,
content creation, you've kind
of tried it. You're not really sure.
You're not really sure what to say.
You're not sure what type of format of
videos you should be doing.
But better yet,
similar to how you didn't really know what
YouTube was, you still
don't know how to use YouTube to then
bolster your business.
So here are some
that you can have for free.
One of which is like what I'm doing here,
talking about using the description.
If people are watching from TV,
which you can see in the analytics,
you might want
to put a QR code up on the screen.
For those of you watching this on the TV,
we
haven't put a QR code up on the screen,
so please go to your mobile and use the
link. There is the community wall,
which is a very exciting feature to
YouTube
that's about a year old. So
when you're scrolling through YouTube,
you see static
pictures,
and those pictures you can put copy,
you can put text on it.
So if any of you are traveling,
and let's say your videographer goes on
holiday for
a week. Oh my God, what am I going to do,
mate? Make some community posts.
Get some clever little photos,
put them out, make a little carousel,
give a little
bold bit of copy,
repurpose it on LinkedIn,
Instagram threads, whatever you want.
You can even have no call to actions in
your videos because the community wall
doesn't just get fed to people
that follow you.
It also goes to colder audiences.
There are some channels
that grow their channels just using those
community wall
threads. We have live streams,
which you could then use to say to people,
"Hey,
give me your email address.
We're going live on Sunday the 15th to
talk about
YouTube. Give me your email address.
I'll send you a link sooner to the time."
Really what you're doing is twofold.
One, you're getting data from people.
Two, you're very cleverly saying, "Hey,
we're going live in three hours.
We're going live in one hour.
We're going live in 15 minutes," to make
sure people
turn up to the live stream. Then even
if people don't turn up to your live
stream,
this is what we do.
We then send them an offer via email for
the same offer the
people that attended it.
Then you can run paid ads to your post
that promotes the
live stream so that you can get a lot of
people interested because it comes from
value, right?
So let's say you're a jujitsu black belt.
Ten of the most popular escapes.
Ten of the most popular submissions.
How to get your blue belt,
how to get your purple belt,
how to force a promotion,
whatever your thing is.
We're going live on this day to discuss
it.
Paid ads, organic post, sign up,
get email addresses, do
the live stream, make it really,
really good. Make it full of information.
Follow-up email.
Here's the free resources.
Here's some free assets.
Oh, by the way,
if you want to be coached by me, this
is how much it costs.
The videographer could say Hey guys,
next Saturday at 9:00
PM BST,
I'm going to show you all the editing
tricks, how to implement
shortcuts,
and how to speed up your editing time
using
keyboard shortcuts,
which I will give you for free on
that live stream.
Organically, you get some sign-ups,
get some email addresses,
you might run some
paid ads. Hey, my name's Declan. I'm 23.
I work with some of the biggest creators
in Australia, and I'm going to teach you
how to edit so well
that they pay you more than what you
invoice.
So YouTube is this massive tool
that you have there to do this,
to do your lead
generation for you,
to get your email addresses,
to sell to people.
And one way to think of it is this,
not everyone on YouTube can afford your
services.
You guys watching this right now,
I know that 90 to 95%
of you can't afford my course. Cool.
But I'm going to keep putting content out
there, like this, for free, so the
95% of you can just learn it.
But then the 5% who can afford the course
will go,
"I'm giving this guy my money because he
obviously knows my problems." Cool.
We're going to move to the next stage now.
Sorry, this is going to be a painful edit.
Do you want to edit this with AI?
You know, where you can use the plugin
and just-
Yeah
... chop all the bits?
Then you might just have to walk through
it.
We'll try it.
He's getting paid by the hour. He's like,
"No, I'll do it properly." The biggest
mistake people make, even
if they understand YouTube, is packaging.
It's the thing I've struggled with the
most.
Titles, thumbnails, titles, thumbnails.
Before we hit record on this,
we had to sit down
and decide what the title was for
this and what the thumbnail
was going to be for this, so
that the introduction made
sense, so the content makes sense,
absolutely everything.
I can't express this enough. This
is what I learned from Ed.
Title and thumbnail first. Title
and thumbnail first.
Even take the picture
and write down the thumbnail so
that you know
what the first few things
are to say in the video.
So for instance, today,
the title of this video should be alluding
to the fact that
I no longer use my big channel.
I need to pay that off in the introduction
because
if my introduction was, "Hi,
my name's James Smith, and I'm from
the UK, but I live in Australia,
and in this video today..." People
are like, "Fuck
off, mate.
I really want to understand why the hell
you're not using the half a
million subscribers you have on YouTube."
And without understanding your title and
thumbnail,
it makes it very difficult to pay off.
Do those things first.
Make several thumbnails.
Make several titles. Have a look.
See what's working. There
is new technology at the moment.
They're integrating it a bit into YouTube,
but there's a website called
thumbnailtest.co.uk
or thumbnailtest.com where you can
connect your YouTube to this website,
and it changes your title
and thumbnails on
the hour, every hour,
and then gives you analytics on what
was your click-through
rate, what was the average view duration,
and you can start to understand what
different titles and thumbnails
are doing to your audience.
For instance, on that one video
that I told you generated
$3,000 of rev once I changed the title,
I then made
five variations.
I made $13.6 million as a PT,
as a personal trainer, as a fitness coach,
as a fitness business.
I then rotated those titles around every
hour on the hour for 25
days.
So I can get an indication not just what
works for that video, but for
other videos,
and it turns out the word PT works
and outperformed everything else.
And it's interesting because sometimes
some titles will get you a better
click-through rate, so more people click,
but the average view duration is lower.
So you need to decide as a creator what's
more important, having less people watch
for longer or having more people watch for
less.
Which will bring us onto the next thing.
The real daddy,
[whispering] the real daddy,
on YouTube at the moment,
as far as trends, is AVD,
average view duration.
This video, there's a lot of waffle.
I'm just off the cuff,
and the edit time is going to be
horrendous.
But if people watch on average for a long
time, that is the main
metric YouTube cares about.
Because you might have great packaging
and a shit
video,
but if you can get people to listen to
what you're saying for long periods
of time, this is why binge effects
are so powerful.
Let's say all your videos are 10 minutes,
but on average, people watch two and a
half of them,
your average view duration will be 25
minutes, which is the same as
creating a one-hour documentary,
and the average person watched 25 minutes.
So whether or not you get your average
view duration sessions up by having lots
of
videos that they binge
or through having longer videos
that people watch
more through,
it kind of equates to the same thing.
The benefit of having multiple videos
and a binge session is that
you've now got 10 assets there alluring
cold audiences in.
If you put all your eggs into one big
video,
you've got less opportunity to do it.
Now,
another thing that's very popular to boost
average view duration and binge
sessions is that you guys should know
that the beginning of your video should
often, this one didn't,
have some form of hook.
I suppose the hook of this one
was more in the packaging saying why I'm
no longer
using my channel that has this many.
That is a type of hook because it creates
inquisites within your mind as to why is
that, and you need to pay
that off by watching the video.
The hook is there.
Then what usually happens in a
well-scripted video, which this isn't,
is you have
some kind of setup,
and then you set up what's happening in
the video.
Then just before you pay it off,
you might go into a B story or whatever.
Then towards the end of the video,
we need to pay off the setup.
What happens?
If it's a challenge,
did they succeed the challenge?
If they didn't, whatever it is.
Then at the end of a video,
we often have an outro.
However, a lot of top creators,
especially Ed, my sensei in this
space, instead of having an outro,
will take a hook and position it at the
end of
the video.
So let's say we did a video on average
view duration.
I could be like, "What
is average view duration, and why
is it blowing up channels
around the world?" Whatever.
Then we go into the average view duration
video.
Then instead of saying at the end, "Hey,
guys, thank you for watching my video on
average view duration," I could say,
"But what is the biggest thing that's
impacting average view duration
that people aren't really thinking about?
And if people were to apply this,
they could double if not triple the amount
of
views they get. Well,
if you want to know what that thing is,
you're going to have
to watch this video."
And what they're doing
is they're setting up a hook to
another video,
and that's where you have end cards.
Whenever you see those little links at the
end of a video, it's called an end card.
And when you really want to get binge
sessions, which we don't really do on this
channel as much because I'm chaotic
and don't plan enough,
is you get someone from
one video to watch another. And
if you can get people to do that,
it's going to
massively impact the average amount of
time people are viewing videos on your
channel.
So average view duration on top of
packaging is probably the most
important thing.
And then the last thing
that we're going to talk about, can't give
it all away for free, is probably this
was the hardest thing for me to accept
on top of the thing
that I thought YouTube
was just a place to post long-format
videos. I just thought it was a place
that you put sideways videos,
like landscape.
I'm from a portrait kind of background.
You know what I mean?
I'm an Instagram, Facebook,
TikTok type of guy.
I'm a short-form content creator.
And I was resistant to this for a long
time.
But when I just dropped my ego and,
see what I'm doing here,
I'm setting you up.
When I just accepted
that I wasn't as good as I thought I
was at content
creation, and I could start doing this,
some of my videos really blew up, and that
is scripting. Because off the cuff, sure,
I know you're watching this going,
"James, what a guy. No teleprompter,
nothing." But when you script a
video,
not only do you get a really good amount
of information out, not only can
you create a backbone of content similar
to writing a book.
When you write a book, you're like, "Cool,
here's 20 topics I want to talk about."
You flesh it out,
you end up with 40 topics.
The same thing happens.
The best YouTubers are the best writers.
Better yet,
you can then go through your script,
reread it, and go, "Oh, I forgot
about this. Oh,
I forgot about that." Better yet,
you can take that script, you can
put it into ChatGPT,
you can get it to write it better.
Better yet,
you can download transcripts from other
creators.
Go to ChatGPT, go, "Here's my script.
Here's a script of the best-performing
video in this niche.
What things have I missed from
that script that you think I should put in
mine?"
Then it will tell you, and you go, "Okay,
where throughout my script shall I put
these?" And it will do it all for you.
Then all you need to do on the day
is turn up.
You can then have your little remote,
like this one is, that press start, stop,
and
You can read a teleprompter. Now,
you'll realize that the best YouTubers in
the
world aren't the best YouTubers,
they're the best writers,
and they're the best to
understand what concepts of value
that they need to deliver to people.
Then they're the best ones at
understanding how they can package
that to make it
clickable, and how to present that so
that people continue watching it.
And better yet, on top of that, they
are the best creators of understanding how
all of those things can attribute people's
traffic towards the
product or service that they're selling.
Which in mind just so happens to be
conveniently that I'm bringing out a
course on
helping creators on YouTube.
But that's not even what I want from this
video.
Instead, as I've alluded to before,
I have 30 ways in 30 days
that I think could
really benefit your business, and
if you click on the link in the
description, you can get those 30 ways.
There'll be also another link to my
mentorship, which helps you through email
marketing, short-form content creation,
long-form content creation, sales funnels.
And the very last thing I'd say,
instead of trying to set you off into
another
video is,
if you let me know what problems you
are facing with YouTube and content
creation in the comments,
I will not only answer your comments,
but I will then
properly strategize a follow-up video to
this where I delve into all of
the issues that you face there. That was,
how long was that?
This only supposed to be a five-minute
video.
That was just me rambling about some of
the things that I think are important to
YouTube.
I've created a whole course on it.
But if you don't want to give me your
money, that's also fine.
You can just stay around
and enjoy the free content,
and one of these days, I'll
get you. Thanks for watching. Peace